this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
sea radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society software Magazine
online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio
I'm your host Jeff Doolittle I'm excited
to invite Adam dimitrick as our guest on
the show today for an exploration of
event modeling as an approach to
requirements Gathering and system design
Adam is over three decades experience in
Information Systems software development
and architecture along with open source
platforms Open Standards and digital
sovereignty in the last 15 years he's
focused on ledger-based and event-driven
architectures he is the author and
inventor of event modeling
the approach is revolutionizing how
information systems are described Adam
is also a core contributor to event
sourcing and cqrs theory and practice
since 2008. this included introducing
paxos to the approach and helping with
the Microsoft patterns and practices
cqrs journey book
he is one of the top one percent
contributors on stack Overflow for
Version Control including holding one of
the three gold badges on the subject
over the last seven years he has built a
successful consultancy specializing in
authoring event-driven systems Adam
welcome to the show thanks Jeff glad to
be here people in the software industry
have been Gathering requirements and
designing systems for decades now
so where does the need for a different
approach arise oh well it arose for me
by trying to do a lot as in my
introduction you said I I had my own
company to start and as any startup
knows funds are hard to come by and I
just noticed the overhead of specifying
software was quite high so the Magic
Moment happened when I noticed if we
think about systems from the events
perspective then we are able to do more
with less and so out of that realization
spun out a new format that was lighter
weight and still gave all the benefits
of all of the other practices such as
user stories
Etc that you may have going all the way
through as we'll cover in the episode
Down to project management maintenance
Etc so event modeling sounds like in
this history of kind of an Eventing
approach as a relatively more recent
development you've been doing it for a
while of course but it's probably new to
some of our list listeners as well but
how does it kind of relate when we think
about the history of information systems
like how we got started with collecting
and defining information and then how
does it kind of fit in that flow right
so good point the information systems
are nothing new to humanity we've had
information systems for thousands of
years long before computers and so I
often talk about this mismatch that we
go through as we you know start using
computers in the very limited form that
they allowed us shortly after vacuum
tubes and when transistors and
integrated circuits happened I think in
my mind anyway I wasn't born yet but
when I look at the type of work that was
described and the systems and how they
worked and how they're described really
focused on this incredible jump in
productivity the transistor gave us an
incredible boost to the processing speed
and we you know we talk about Moore's
law all the time about how ships are
getting faster so that was a real shot
in the arm for information systems to
have everything digitized
and unfortunately we didn't have the
same shot in the arm for storage and so
we lost this Ledger way of thinking
about Information Systems because up to
that point it was really record keeping
that allowed Information Systems to
scale
to be organized to find out why things
aren't going right Etc so the system of
account was almost like information
systems were accounting systems for
information instead of money this
problem I mean this is not a problem but
this real great advantage of being able
to process data really quickly showed a
disadvantage of having a really
expensive storage and I always use the
example of the 10 megabyte IBM hard
drive that cost you know a million
dollars back in 1954 or 56 I forget the
exact there's a very famous photo you
can look up online if you just look up
IBM hard drives in the 50s and I think
the thing took you know thirty thousand
dollars per month to run and it was you
know the size of a small room so you
know obviously if you want to keep every
record of every state change as an event
that's not going to happen your boss is
not going to allow you to buy five of
those he says make do with one and so
that's where we started you know erasing
data and data normalization was
incredibly important and in those days
because of this mismatch of how quickly
information was produced versus how
expensive it was to store information so
you know in the grand scheme of things
it's this mismatch that we're going
through of course now you know in your
phone you have these uh this ability to
hold so much information in your phone
you could run you know a global company
from the 50s in your phone no problem so
that you know Moore's law on the side of
storage has definitely caught up in
recent decades but we've definitely set
a bunch of ruts in the road that painted
information systems that were digitized
as different than information systems
that weren't digitized and I think it's
time to move back because we're by
default throwing information away which
is not a good default to managing
Information Systems well let's take that
and help our listeners first with a
brief definition of what is an event
when we talk about event modeling and
then we can connect that back to some of
the things you've shared about data
storage limitations and sort of the
history of things what is exactly an
event sure so an event is a really good
way of saying fact there's many probably
many different words one could come up
with as to what happens in the timeline
when we're automating Information
Systems so you know if someone signs up
for a website or someone approves those
you know an insurance policy or someone
files a claim for insurance these are
things on a timeline that happen and
they capture certain pieces of
information now our technical Minds go
straight into like uh what tables do I
need to update so that these queries
come back with the right thing that's
moving way too far ahead if we think of
the way Information Systems used to be
back to my previous point we see that
this fact stored on a ledger is really
kind of a raw data that's still not
formed by any opinion and in its raw
State this fact or event can then be
transcribed to whatever your needs are
and so we get to do a lot more with
events compared to what we do with what
we think the event is and forcing them
into traditional I use traditional in
the very short term obviously are
digital traditional format of most
likely table structures in rdbms where
we're quite opinionated as to how it's
supposed to be divided so it's kind of a
move back and you know events are also
something that are much more human in
terms of you know they're the components
of a story and their brains work really
well I go into this quite a bit in a lot
of what I teach is to really use
mechanisms that are really human and
more friendly to human and you see this
in storytelling
in the linearization of what's happening
and of course in the text sector we're
quite inundated with I guess activity
diagrams and flow charts and graphs and
graphs aren't you know easy to remember
for humans it's stories that people
remember and memory is quite important
in communication because what good is
communication if you don't recall what
was communicated right it's like oh this
person speaks eloquently describing this
graph but then when I go back to my desk
I have to keep referencing that graph
again and I have a mismatch of what's in
my head versus what was communicated and
so having a story aspect to everything
you're trying to communicate allows the
recollection of what was communicated to
be higher and I think that's quite
important because it does limit the
amount of interactions that are needed
and so you can focus on high quality
Communications and use the rest of your
time to actually do work so you know
we're all kind of you know death by a
thousand meetings in today's industry
and so anything that can help help
remove that problem you know will have
in my opinion something that allows
better recollection and anything that's
discussed or collaborated upon to have a
better longevity in their cognitive low
and naturally fits in their heads so
that's you know that's kind of like the
human aspect of why events are important
but more you know the other good side of
events is that they also are a really
good home for information from the
digital perspective you have immutable
storage all these really good technical
aspects for easier caching you know you
talk to anyone about functional
programming and immutability they'll
tell you you know 100 different benefits
and so yeah why not just obviously use
that for everything else as well and if
the two go hand in hand you're also
going to encourage a much better
approach to managing information in on
the technical side I hope that answers
it I think it answers a lot that might
spin up a few questions for listeners as
well and I'll add some links in the show
notes to some of the concepts that you
described functional programming
immutability and things of that nature
but one of the things that's
particularly interesting to me is first
the idea of how this is a human oriented
approach which reminds me of one of the
things I'm apt to say when I present
which is we've discovered the problem
and the problem is people and the
solution is people and that's the
problem but what it sounds like you're
describing with event modeling is we're
actually empowering people to be able to
have
something that fits the way that the
human mind works as we're tackling some
of these problems is that correct yeah
yeah exactly so like I said something
that's more easily digestible by humans
is much better so event modeling allows
you to basically look at a storyboard
like you would for a movie with the top
swimlings being what the actors what the
scenes are and what the actors are doing
and what the key frames are showing you
know key points in the story to get the
whole movie to the gel together but down
below you have the plot which is the
data you know you could have I I always
pick on Kevin Costner and Waterworld and
but you can have a very beautiful movie
but the plot is just very bad and you're
not going to enjoy it right so you gotta
have both that's kind of like a very
simple way of me introducing event
modeling to people is think of a movie
storyboard and both are important but
fundamentally for this communication if
you know the reality is that a lot of us
are visual and another the other half of
us is really analytical so you have to
have both to really tell instruct people
or explain to people how the system
works or how your imagined system is
going to work when you're done with the
project and that's to have that Vision
an end-to-end Vision at least so that
everyone is pointing in the same
direction and it requires that view both
from the visual aspects for people that
are more visual even their jobs are
require them to be visuals such as
designers ux folks Etc to the people
that are on the architecture side that
need to know where the data lives and
their slas and when do things move from
system a to system B and how does that
data transform and of course this is all
done by example so the other part of
event modeling is that if it heavily
does rely on the history the successful
history of specification by example and
behavior driven development which is you
know takes the approach of show enough
examples with real data you know reels
screenshots of what things are supposed
to look like along a workflow and people
are smart enough trusted people to
interpret that example as a good enough
specifications because our minds are
actually quite good at filling in the
blank in fact you know I keep talking
about stories and why those are
important but our brains are quite slow
processors and we do well you know but
they're quite smart processors or slow
processors but they're incredibly
Advanced and being able to fill in the
gaps our eyes are not cameras that are
you know 104 megapixels and do 60 frames
a second we're actually quite low spec
yet our brains fill in the blanks quite
well so you can liken that two days you
know processors and phones that allow
enhancement of photos not just using the
raw input of the sensor our eyes ears
and senses are and even memory work the
same way we're we're a very low you know
five megapixel camera with really really
good processing and so a storyline like
that like a storyboard with the
keyframes both for data and for what
people are seeing is the low-fi picture
that has high value because the
advantage to the Lo-Fi is that you're
not spending a year in it right so going
back to the history of specifying
software you can go if you over specify
things you you know probably not with
good results will end up implementing
all seven uml diagrams and spend a whole
year there before you even touched code
and and that's the straw man that people
throw in for agile all the time is like
not a big design up front you're going
to spend a year doing all this and I'm
not going to get you know feedback on
what you're doing you might be building
the wrong thing or the market might have
moved on you and things like this so we
need something that you know if you're
really good at event modeling we've done
event modeling sessions for that lasted
15 minutes right or an afternoon if you
get really good with it like anything
else you can find you know a real
shorthand for it yourself as well but
you get the same benefits so you know
internally we definitely have our own
format for event modeling if we're not
working for a particular client that
we'll use but generally we want the
standardized approach for event modeling
so that you get some ways of getting
vlog velocity and Cadence to you know
how a system works so you mentioned some
broad ideas of what event model entails
you mentioned a storyboard which you
know like a movie storyboard I imagine
is going to have visualizations that can
kind of tell the visual story of what's
Happening Here and then you talk about
the plot kind of being what undergirds
that whole process so let's maybe dig a
little bit more into that tell us some
about the language of event modeling in
other words what are the artifacts or
the items or the entities whatever they
might be that help someone to actually
Define an event model right so the core
component of an event model is what I
refer to as a slice it's really a
workflow step As you move from left to
right on the timeline an event model is
meant to allow you to analyze each step
with a guarantee that only one thing is
happening there so a workflow step can
be one of two things it's either where
you're changing the state of the entire
system but ideally obviously that is
going to be shown does the state change
in just one subsystem in all of the
systems that make up the whole solution
so it's either the state change step or
a view into the state that's necessary
to facilitate some information being
brought back either to a user or an
automated process and that's kind of the
highest level kind of component is and
the most important component is
identifying the state changes and the
state views in the system each of those
is made up of or state change it's most
commonly the UI having a button pressed
then going to an intention or a command
to change the state such as please can I
register as a user here's the
information collected from the web page
and then the acknowledgment of that you
know it passed all the validation your
emails formatted correctly Etc whatever
your business rules are it then flows
down to the event and the event is the
only way that you store State changes
it's this Ledger approach that you can
then analyze them so far in this event
model these are the events that have
been stored so far it is the truth of
what happened in the system and you can
make decisions in further steps later
based on that and so those components
are you know we use color coding for
these so the uis are usually wireframes
or figma artifacts that designers have
already created if you're lucky enough
to have those if you're doing a existing
system you can just do screenshots of
the existing system to show that the
command is blue so visually you can see
that it's the intent to change the
system State and the events are orange
on Miro although if we're doing this in
person I usually switch that to Yellow
because yellow stickies are easier to
find in stores
I think there's been a lot of
event-driven approaches that kind of
standardized on orange as being an event
so we just adopted that now the other
side to an individual step is looking at
the state view which is really again a
screen that's kind of showing maybe a
list of movie tickets available or
concert tickets but going backwards on
this one that comes from a green box
which is an opinion of what the events
meant so it's a state view in other
words you can have a whole bunch of
steps before where an administrator
added a whole bunch of tickets for sale
they're all individual events on the
timeline but there is this live report
green box that kind of listens for all
of them and says oh well right now we
have five different concerts going on in
the future you can buy tickets for and
so that green box will have a
traditional kind of maybe a table that
shows all the tickets and kind of
information that's needed to make that
page look nice and of course it's joined
to those events those orange boxes so
there's definitely a Cadence like an
opinion as to the flow and what arrows
can connect to anything and by forcing
you know the UI or API to hit a blue box
then have to connect to an orange box
then have to go to back to a green box
and then back out to the API these rules
of what can connect to what help ensure
that there's very few patterns that you
have now if you have very few patterns
that allows you to have a really nice
large sample size for just how long your
team's taking to get this automated and
so this opinion of being able to dissect
each you know system that you have into
a standard set of components is kind of
the unit of work and done is done
problem we've been trying to tackle for
a long time and I think the secret has
been to look at State changes at the
right level not have to go dive deep
into an implementation of a class that's
highly technical which you know helps
keep this as something you can share
with all the rules in the organization
so anyone that cares about the project
can understand what the system is doing
this diagram has nothing technical in it
it's simply looking at how information
in your system changes over time none of
these boxes have any artifacts that are
technical when it's being done properly
so of course people have used it for
technical purposes on technical teams
but the intent of it is to really gel
the entire organization together and
break down walls between different roles
when you're working on projects because
that's the real issue with is the
communication problems and the multiple
standards of different specs that we
have oh this is a design dock only ux
people can look at it or designers can
look at it oh this is a uml diagram all
the technical people Architects and
developers look at it that's creating
silos and it doesn't help really
coalesce the whole vision of the system
and doesn't put people on the same page
event modeling is useful for all those
roles maybe not to the same extent as a
detailed uml diagram for a class set of
classes Etc but that doesn't matter they
can if they want do some extra
diagramming on the Whiteboard and share
some things with them but the contract
between all the rules is that the given
time in a workflow the state of the
system is this and we can all shake
hands on it and agree and I think that's
a fine enough grain of detail to guide
the project and both from the details of
implementation but also to the larger
vision of like how far along are we on
this large one-year project and also you
know just for people thinking that this
has to be all done at once at the
beginning that's not true either it's a
kind of like a token of work so you can
take a totally agile approach to this
and only you know think about the next
few iterations that you're going to do
and model those and but the state change
is your token and you can actually say
hey how expensive is refactoring going
to be you can actually say it you can
follow the lines and say you know what
I'm going to have to revisit those other
three workflow pieces from the work from
you know two weeks ago so I'm not just
giving you an extra large T-shirt size
or a medium T-shirt size I'm actually
giving you something more Concrete in
terms of the complexity of what I'm
about to do when I'm at the stand up so
it's very compatible with all these
other ways and think it makes
communication incredibly fast and we
don't you kind of remove a lot of the
subjectivity where you know it's kind of
sold us on a really you know
unopinionated way hey anything works
just as long as you get feedback it's
like well we want to give some structure
to that so we're not you know taking the
bad side of that which is an entirely
subjective opinions of how things are we
want to tie it down to the real world
you know impact of what that is in the
solution everyone's working on so
ultimately it sounds like event modeling
is less of a technical solution if it is
at all it's more of a human
communication approach absolutely and
Technical people are humans believe it
or not so I know some people might not
think so but yes exactly so yeah like
you said before it's a people problem
and so any tooling that we can invent or
make that helps us be better humans at
our jobs and a lot of that is in teams
and larger organizations is
communication and so I haven't found
anything really that compares to event
modeling and I never actually set out to
create event modeling event modeling is
the distillation of a lot of the other
tools into a common format that does the
same job you know 80 90 100 percent of
what those other tools may do so you
know anything from issue tracking
project you know Sprint planning any of
those things are things that we
internally do ourselves and so you know
my team is really a guinea pig for the
last seven years of like all right let's
see if you can do everything using this
methodology and so the answer is an
astounding yes we can and it's
compatible with others obviously not
everyone's gonna just drop what they
know and start using a new methodology
but there are ways to link them together
and have these slices that I was talking
about be represented by and jira tickets
if you're still using jira somewhere
then you can definitely map those in
fact it can probably automate your
canvases their digital canvases too with
their apis to create the Geo tickets for
you and vice versa and if you finish
something you might be able to push
something to your digital workflow your
event model that'll Mark that slices
having been done and maybe even show
visually with some initials as to who
worked on it I think there's so many
neat ways to really extend other tools
and other Concepts that were you know
we're using to event modeling I mean you
could hook it up to your CI CD pipeline
if someone's done with a particular
feature that is expressed as a set of
slices when those are done you know you
can have a listener on GitHub or
whatever your repository is and then
Mark that off so yeah lots of you know
this is just scratching the surface over
the last three years I mean when they
wrote the article initially was 2018 it
really took off it was a medium article
and that took off quite well I was
surprised I was getting phone calls from
emails from the blue and I didn't know
what was going on and ended up being on
Hacker News I didn't know someone posted
that article on Hacker News and it made
it to the first page and in the top
story I think it was October of 2018. so
you know at that point I said to myself
well I have to kind of make at least a
website dedicated to it so
eventmodeling.org started and I just put
that Medium article in there cleaned it
up a little bit and so it's been you
know it's the rare start when you look
at it it's a very start of this journey
we've only been looking at the
formalized method across other teams
besides us for the last three to four
years you know the the website didn't
really go live until 2019 kind of maybe
a year before covid and so a lot of
things have happened obviously there's
the event modeling done in person versus
online right and so I had to go through
that change as well so there's some
shorthand on the event modeling website
that more applicable to in person and
you kind of be you're a little bit more
thorough when you're doing it digitally
just a couple of small differences but
that's kind of the history yeah and you
connected it too with other human
communication tools which ultimately
that's what tools like GitHub and jira
are for is there to help facilitate
human communication you know over time
and yeah and another one I missed is uh
Storyteller another bdd Frameworks which
really try to bake in the business
language into your fixtures and so that
you have a template for how you describe
your business steps and fill in example
data this takes it to a simpler format
where you don't need tooling for it I
was a big proponent of behavior driven
design of course I still am just in a
different format with all those tools
like cucumber Etc all the things that
you would need for end-to-end testing
and getting stories articulated
correctly that has been replaced for us
at least with event modeling since it
does check off a bunch of other points
so we're kind of killing many birds with
one stone not just two birds with one
stone that's kind of the idea absolutely
this you know this this communication
piece with existing tooling and how
humans connect you know going back to
the fact that we did this on a
shoestring budget at first we didn't
have money for a project manager in
enough you know time to manage jira we
didn't have time to do any of the other
10 things you might find a typical
project so if we had to do just one
thing we had to coalesce all these other
parts from existing tools and make one
methodology or one tool do all of them
and that's how event modeling
organically originated again I said I
never intended to create this it just
happened it was what we discovered while
being you're being asked to make
incredibly High scalable maintainable
Solutions high quality Solutions fast
and cheap it's like oh you just squeeze
the Iron Triangle so hard yes it has to
be good it has to fit good we want all
three or your company doesn't exist
essentially and so that forced us to we
couldn't essentially we couldn't do it
with the existing tools and processes
that you find in software we would have
no business so that's kind of the back
story of event modeling is that it
allows you to do a lot more with a lot
less and what you're cutting out is
really the things that are lower value
in favor of the high value pieces like
we said communication specification
being very you know immune using
immutable ideas about how information is
stored and what facts are stored those
are really good pillars of solid
architecture and I would say that
information architecture is the one that
overarches all the other architectures
because that is essentially what the
purpose of a system is do we get this
information in front of these people are
these people allowed to enter in this
information it's all about you know in
most systems we're talking about point
of sale systems and insurance companies
and 99 of the staff software out there
that we're automating is just automating
our lives you know since computers came
into existence there is the one percent
where someone has a technical side and
they're working on a search algorithm or
they're doing us you know they're
improving doing a pull request for the
docker project or something that's not
where event modeling is necessarily
going to help you but it's going to help
you in the majority of the projects out
there where you're automating our you
know people's lives and the regular
businesses so it sounds like in a way
you were taking prior Concepts ideas
patterns things that were working for
people in the industry but you were also
noticing that there was a lot of
additional heavyweight things or at
least for your context things that
seemed like additional effort additional
work and you try to distill it down to
something simpler and then you needed a
name for what seemed to be working and
that's where event modeling sort of it's
almost like you stumbled into it
discovered it then decided to name it
and it seems kind of similar to you know
Json which was there until somebody said
hey look at this thing I found in
JavaScript Json and it's like we're
already doing it but let's formalize it
and let's name it is that similar to how
event modeling came about it is and a
heavy process that we used in our
company obviously is event sourcing cqrs
domain driven design and then of course
back in 2015 I stumbled across Vaughn
and the Alberto's Workshop format for
event storming which is a way to get
everyone in the same room to talk about
events the whole time I was thinking I
was just doing event
storming correctly and we were using
event storming artifacts to be the
blueprint but it wasn't event storming I
went to
Italy bologna Alberta was nice enough to
invite me there for you know all the
people that were practicing events
storming around the world or at least
leading the cause of it and popularizing
it and you know it was kind of weird
because I said well this is the way we
do it it's way better our projects are
on time we don't have any of these
problems of translating the event
storming artifacts into Solutions and
that's when I saw okay well we're
dropping certain things like we're not
doing policies policies are just you
know not something that we bother
identifying it's already captured in the
naming of processors and other things
read models that we have or stage views
that we have in event modeling and so I
said okay well I guess we're not doing
event storming we're doing something
else that's where the name came from is
that well we're doing something with
events it's not event storming obviously
it's got a much more you know a
different way of a different structure
and it's a little bit more opinionated
to for some benefits being able to
measure your size of projects and and
also Drive implementation directly from
from it so it's not event storming so it
is event something and I said well we're
kind of modeling entire systems so we'll
just call it event modeling and that's
kind of says that's probably a better
name for it anyway so you know from
there it's just was kind of the thing I
thought of in a day and it stuck so so
far no one's really suggested any other
names and most people recognize the
practice by this name now okay so let's
say somebody's familiar with event
storming
well actually let's let's talk about
both if you're not familiar with any of
this stuff but let's say you're familiar
with event storming to some extent start
there what would be different for
somebody who says I want to give event
modeling a try what would change what
would they stop doing what would they
start doing oh yeah that's a great Point
yeah event storming is quite popular
actually event Story made it to the
center of the tech radar by thoughtworks
all right so that was in 2018 I believe
or I think around there was the only
practice to adopt which is crazy out of
the 100 Technologies and approaches that
they review event starring was the only
one that made it to the center so event
storming is kind of a more elaborate
brainstorming phase of event modeling
really so there two are quite compatible
if you're doing event storming already
to your initial brainstorming session
event in event storming is thrown away
after the event storming primarily was
designed to forget that environment for
people to collaborate and get everyone
in the same room for that day to talk
about all the different problems hot
spots and other problems in the problem
space and all of that and get everyone
to get on the same page as to how they
understand the intended system and all
of those things but then it's kind of
thrown away and then people go back to
their desks to go back at least you know
before they added a couple more forms of
event storm but primarily it was about a
discovery process so I thought modeling
has that as a component it doesn't have
things like the key differences doesn't
have policies in it as I said it has a
ways to do the same thing by naming
processes and naming State views to
replace that also it's highly
opinionated event modeling is highly
opinion in terms of the storyboard
aspect the timeline is forward only
event storming allows branching and
other you know connections so it has a
little bit more of a free flow and so
generally if your goal is the same thing
and you want to use event modeling
instead of event storming you're going
to find that you're mostly just
concentrating on events with event
modeling putting them down into a
storyline so that you have some way of
starting to talk about a whole workflow
and get a storyboard going for that
another big difference is that ux and UI
is a first-class citizen in event
modeling so having that visual aspect
and the ux and customer experience at
the top of the list is quite important
because even for back-end heavy
processes there are still visual people
involved in specifying those and
implementing those so even though you
might have you know 12 steps that are
entirely behind the scenes with no UI on
it you still want to add a UI for a
system operator and admin that may say
oh this process is stuck at this step
this queue is not moving you know
messages or payment requests through or
something like that so it's still
important so event modeling really does
focus on the customer ux experience that
type of mindset all the way through it
never loses it and I think that's one of
its strengths is that never stops that
human connection with how we as humans
even if it's systems operators or
programmers see things I mean I would
put sometimes an event like a log a
console log as one of the screens in one
of the swim lanes because at this point
yeah there may be a backed up system
here and it's going to be a system admin
that's going to be looking at a log and
I want to show that visually that this
part of the workflow is kind of
treacherous you're going to have this
actor that's the system admin as the
only one that can help you you can
visually see that right even and it's
helpful to the system but it's also
helpful to people that are using the
overall system that hey this is a highly
technical part of the solution if there
are problems this is where we you know
go to second level support maybe so yeah
we can definitely just talk the whole
time about the two differences but I
think that kind of rounds it out about
you know event storming is really about
the one day collaboration event modeling
is about having a schematic for the life
of the project and then once the project
is finished it's a schematic that you
use to maintain the system that's the
intent of the event mode it's really to
you know how you had TVs back in the day
day with vacuum tubes you would have a
schematic of the circuit board on the
back of the TV so when a vacuum tube
burnt out the TV repairman would know
exactly you know which wires to check
where the connections are and which
vacuum tube to replace when burnt out
that's a maintainable system it comes
with a schematic I mean even my
Commodore 64 back in the day the large
manual that you could buy for it had a
fold out schematic of all the chips on
there the whole circuit was a full you
know you would open the last cover the
back cover of the manual and you'd fold
out into thirds or sixes or whatever but
it would be a really large sheet that
would just show you the you know how
your computer was put together so what
we're doing is the same thing for
information systems and I think we've
got the right you know the right level
of scope which is the state changes to
do the exact same thing okay and I think
that answers the question a bit as well
about what a team would do if they're
starting from nothing and they want to
do event modeling they could still use
event storming they could maybe skip the
policy portion of it it but essentially
you still want to have a discovery
process for what are the business yeah
exactly that's the storming part exactly
yeah the storming part yeah you can do
either or like I mean if people are
already familiar with event storming
it's really easy to translate policies
into names of processors and things like
that and just drop the purple stickies
and transform it very very easily in
fact a lot of our projects have been
initial event storming projects where
the people were stuck on the
implementation moving from event
storming to implementation so there's a
number of projects that we moved forward
because the event model gave the
schematic that gave them you know the
okay here's how I start coding with
confidence I'm building the right thing
and that we're still using the
ubiquitous language and other things
that we discovered along the way in the
storming part right so when we gather
ideas it's nice to also have a place for
where they plunk in in the future
solution as well so let's transition and
give our listeners a bit of a flavor of
how event modeling is practiced with a
concrete example you've mentioned in a
previous conversation with me that
there's seven steps that a team will go
through as they're doing event modeling
so walk us through those steps and if
you can give us a concrete example in
those steps of maybe even a project that
you've worked on that our listeners can
kind of you know visualize hopefully in
their brain sort of how this process
works oh yeah the seven steps are really
a guideline event modeling is really a
language of how to talk about an
information system but if people don't
know where to start the seven steps are
great to do that so I already mentioned
the first one you kind of brainstorm all
the things that would happen and so you
know we've done a number of projects
that started at this level one of them
was a recruiting company that's
disrupting the industry so they're
allowing people that want to be in the
recruiting space not to have to go work
for one so it's about having independent
recruiters so that required to make sort
of a quote-unquote Marketplace both for
where you post jobs and where people
apply for jobs or the types of work they
want to do and instead of having one
recruiting company go and do that you
know for those companies and for those
people and you can say well here's an
open market where then individual agents
can go and say Hey you know I actually
am quite good at c-sharp and so I see
there's five companies that are looking
for developers and c-sharp and then I
know all these people here say that they
have.net experience but maybe some of
them don't say that they have a c-sharp
experience but I know they'll probably
be a good fit because they seem like
they're seen here and so from that point
the individual agent can then connect
that person to that company whereas a
general kind of buzzword matching
recruiting company will miss that right
so that's a really good cause and of
course individual agents are way less
expensive than recruiting companies so
then if there's a benefit to everyone
it's a win-win-win situation so in this
case I hope everyone understands that
business prospect there for automating a
business so what we did was we got those
events that had to happen such as you
know job application posted or profile
of you know submitted profile for a
developer agent registered all those
different things that happened and then
of course even the management all the
different events that could happen such
as even the payouts you know because
there's a different amount that you get
from the fee that the platform charges
so all those events were brainstormed
and then we put them on a timeline on
physical stickies on the board
and we started to look at well what do
we want these screens to show because we
already have a kind of a so that's the
first step is really just getting the
events down and the second step is get
the events into some sort of a
storyboard order so you know we might
start with the company posting something
and then some agent sign up and then
after that maybe some people finally go
to the website and put up their bios
because they're looking for work and
then the agent starts to look at some
listings on both sides and starts to
match and connect them by email so we
have all of these events in Orange
stickies
across the wall
and then we say well how do they do
these things you know what do they have
on the screen that they're looking at
and so we get the other part of the
storyboard then that's step two is get
the UI up there but ux is really
important and sometimes we flip those
two it's this is just one way of doing
it but sometimes we flip those two if
someone already has wireframes in terms
of the screens they want in their system
they already you know have a pretty good
picture in their head we can start with
you know step two and go back to step
one that's fine they're interchangeable
so once you got that step of here are
the how the screens look over time we
always have example data in there so
that people can relate to it we can try
to anyway to make it that's another
important Point actually having example
data allows you to do an audit of if you
have something called information
completeness are you making up facts
where did this information come from do
I have a step somewhere in the past
where someone entered in this
information if I don't I know I've
missed out some important requirements
so it's really good to be able to audit
that without getting into the weeds just
at the information level it's still very
manageable and very light to do that so
it's a nice audit to be able to do so
after that those first two steps kind of
have the storyboard the basics of a
storyboard but then we start to connect
the screens where people are actually
changing the Status system with those
blue boxes and linking them down to an
orange box and anytime that we have an
orange box that kind of appears out of
nowhere we know that there's a process
that we're missing so we start to put in
gears for the processes like oh this
ranking of this person's skill in C
sharp was done via some AI thing that we
you know included well that would be a
gear on the workflow that the system is
doing something for you and so once you
start interrogating the basic storyboard
you start to identify all the blue boxes
and the green boxes I had described
before and those are steps you know
three and four into what's going on in
terms of changing the state
boxes being your commands yeah
intention to change the state of the
system that's right and the orange or
yellow in the real World box which is an
event which is reflecting the fact that
the state of the system did in fact
change and then the green being the
views of the representations of an
opinion on those facts on those events
yeah for example in this case listeners
yeah and in fact that green Buck's a
good example in this recruiting system
as a list of candidates you know that's
a searchable list and you know if you
put in the keyword C sharp you have a
short list of that and obviously one of
the columns in that green box would be
you know skill set or it might be a join
to a table that has skill sets and you
could filter on that with a very simple
query ideally the green box is when
you're implementing kind of like your
select Stars you're kind of like making
those models to be exactly what you need
for that step to be done really quickly
right and then event modeling forces you
to look at a multi-model implementation
which is actually a good way of
deconstructing coupling issues where you
know Jeff you can work on one screen for
the candidates listings and I can look
at the job listings page and we're not
stepping on each other toes because
we're not competing on how a single
table is going to be used for both of
those displays I might be stepping in
your toes or vice versa but if we have
our own projections off of the events
that we totally own you own your green
box and I own my green box we can work
in parallel and really not have to fight
over the formats in those tables because
we have our own and so that's a really
important point because event modeling
does allow a higher level of parallelism
which allows larger teams you know we no
longer go by the pizza size team
internally since we can do a lot more by
understanding where these things are so
back to the point the last step is
really organizing these swim Lanes so
that I may have a candidate system I
might have another system that shows the
job postings and I put those in swim
Lanes down below so all events that
relate to job postings going one swim
Lane all events going for applicants
applicants can go in the swimming that's
if we decide that there's going to be
two subsystems and we do that buy these
swim lanes and likewise on top we
organize those different screens so some
screens may be seen just by job
applicants some screens might be seen by
the agent and some screens might be seen
by the companies putting up jobs so
there would be three swim Lanes at the
top you know all the screens through the
workflow that are shown to a particular
user are shown in their own swimming
that gives you an ability to kind of
interrogate the storyboard as to okay
well we can see this is an agent heavy
you know system we're going to probably
have to have more development here it
actually starts to give you feedback on
where your focus is also it shows you
kind of neat flows through the system a
lot of times our swim lanes for the
events are a Cascade of information
where things kind of are onboarding in
the very first part of the workflow and
they Cascade down to the middle
management of dealing with the
information and then they kind of
cascade down into either sales or
reporting domains at the very end so
it's kind of neat to see the progression
of information where the connections are
so it's a very highly you know visual
organized workflow to show you you know
exactly where the handoffs are and it
does you know we call it Conway's law
because it's those communication
Pathways that Conway really identified
and you see those right in front of you
here it's you know when you have people
organized to develop these systems which
teams are going to talk to one another
and what information what contracts are
important to make sure they're talking
about those ahead of time and you can
focus on them so Conway's law really
plays a big role in how we build these
systems we really
sensitive to when we have handoffs of
information from one team to another
right and just to remind listeners
Conway's law essentially states that
organizations will create systems that
mimic their own communication structures
so since event modeling is a tool for
human communication it sounds like what
you're saying is let's get Conway's law
on our side working for us yeah exactly
or at least you know always think about
it and not ignore it as I think a lot of
times happens in the industry and then
we pay the price by having you know
really awkward project implementations
so definitely Melancholy the the whole
industry of a big favor by identifying
this long ago and those that understand
its implications are far better off in
how they put systems together for sure
and what I appreciate about event
modeling is you're showing not telling
in other words it's one thing to tell
people Conway's law matters but what
you're doing is you're showing you don't
even need to necessarily tell someone
Conway's law exactly they're going to
get the benefits of Conway's law whether
they recognize it or not you bring up a
really good point because one of the
things with limited budget that we
couldn't do we couldn't really educate a
lot of people not only just on Conway's
law we can educate people on domain
driven design or event sourcing or any
sorts of things so one of the things
that event modeling does is it starts
out with the goals of all those
practices being shown as the artifact so
someone can do event modeling for a year
and then say hey wait a minute I have
domain driven design these look like
bounded context wait a second this is an
aggregate I have you know transactional
Integrity on this wow so they can go
backwards kind of stumble Cramer their
way into it and fall backwards into
domain-driven design and that was kind
of out of necessity like I said the
luxury to be able to say hey team go
study domain driven design go study
event sourcing go study cqs go study
Conway's law go study you know hexagonal
architecture that would take a long time
to do and to understand so we needed to
start off with an example and these
slices are formulated exactly
specifically for this purpose so that
they end up fit getting any of these
really good approaches that takes time
to learn right and when someone you know
is new or Junior you don't want to have
to wait for them to level up you want
them to go through the proper motions
and to backfill why they're doing it
later but also do that from a really
good place not just that someone told
them to but that they have a convention
that allows them to move quickly through
that as they're learning and not be
worried about you know blowing up the
system like these slices in our
implementation are done through event
sourcing and so they do contain you know
they're small if there's an explosion
that's small if someone implements a
slice badly it's just replaced you're
not really likely to really destroy the
system if you're working on a team
that's doing this yeah and that's what I
refer to as complexity containment you
know you've contained complexity when
there's a significant change in your
system and it's isolated to a small
portion of your system and you know you
have a bad design when a change in your
system affects multiple parts of your
system
it does tremendously and you know
combining this with implementations that
are event driven and events sourced
specifically where we don't lose any
information we always have a breadcrumb
trail to go back to so event modeling
really does allow you to push forward in
your event-driven architecture goals and
your event source and goals it's been
you know I think some people have said
that it's the only way to learn cqs and
event sourcing properly that's the
benefit for them and that's not me and I
was just kind of looking on Twitter like
what people are saying about it not even
people they didn't mention me so just
looking for event modeling they found
these cool quotes that like okay this is
like this is how I learned how to do
event sourcing properly is because I
described a system using event modeling
and you know others have said that oh
event modeling allowed me to you know
start you know my project within days
instead of having false starts for
forever so event modeling was always
used to restart failed projects so we
had you know a lot of large projects
that were Do or Die situations and
they're already past their second
attempt at implementation
and coming in with event modeling really
allowed everyone to get on the same page
and brought out the misunderstandings
and it brought out the incomplete pieces
that in terms of specifications and that
identification of those pieces and doing
something that Chris Condren is a CTO of
event store brought up is this
information completeness I mentioned it
earlier but it's quite important
especially for non-trivial systems being
able to trace through where each value
in the system came from where it's shown
this kind of audit this is the highest
responsible level you can do this kind
of audit without you know if you go the
other way you're into uml and then
you're you know to to have a
specification that's on the class level
method level is going to take a long
long time but focusing on state still
allows you to that completeness in a
much much shorter time and it's you know
he coined that term at the time that he
was helping a company go through exactly
this and not a very non-trivial sized
project which I talk about sometimes
which dealt with trading on the New York
Stock Exchange another like not trivial
systems you know billions of dollars at
stake and to have those types of
problems be solved by event modeling was
really good and by the way this is not a
Magic Bullet it doesn't remove work like
you still have to work but what it does
allow you to do is to organize your work
and really remove unnecessary detail to
a responsible level so that you can get
through the work at the highest
efficiency that's kind of how I would
say it's because a lot of people say oh
it sounds like a silver bullet that
you're talking about here it's like no
it's kind of like a way of doing things
at the most responsible level of speed
with retaining the quality that you can
still attain those same goals
right it's a way of working it's not
eliminating the fact that you have to
work but also it sounds like the goal is
as well is to refine your work so you're
focusing on the most important things
and shedding a lot of things that might
otherwise just be
unnecessary or not as helpful like maybe
maybe there's some value in them but
it's just not as high as the value of
what you're focusing on well I would say
that all of the different practices are
are valuable but I think the time that
it takes to
you know fill them out completely is a
non-trivial um and it's it's extra time
so so we you know that's a precious
thing we can we want to preserve so um
event modeling does allow the the
responsible level of ignoring
implementation detail
um but sticks uh the stakes in the
ground at important points such as state
Transitions and state views to not go
too high up and just be hand waving kind
of uh uh really you know ethics user
stories that can be interpreted in too
many ways and don't give enough guidance
so you know that's and you know even
just executing on projects like people
love the fact that they can follow uh an
event model step by step and when you're
implementing you you're not distracting
you don't need to use the Pomodoro
Technique you don't need to do these
things when you're concentrating on a
blue box or this screen you finish it
you move on to where the arrow points to
next Etc so it's a really good backbone
to the efforts actual everyday work
workload that that someone might have in
implementing a solution that guidance
gives you all the check boxes you're
looking for from from jira or from your
standups and all of that like you know
we don't have stand-ups because we know
on the event model who's done what and
we we do that on a push pull basis when
there's a comment on the mural board
that someone's you know hit a blocker
that blocker is immediately taken care
of by anyone else that's looking at the
event model because they come up as red
comment Bubbles and we just make sure
that there's no red comment bubbles ever
on the event model
it's faster than stand-ups right those
feedback loops we kind of squeeze them
so tight that they disappeared because
we're instead of getting feedback
between people and communicating
um we're collaborating and collaboration
is real time the the feedback loop is so
tight it doesn't exist if you can
imagine right collaboration yeah yeah
and it also sounds asynchronous which
especially in a world of distributed
teams and that's not going away to be
able to have that collaborative approach
now to be able to asynchronously respond
to things as well seems like a huge
benefit also thank you for bringing that
up because we've had a ton of projects
that are very successful that were
globally distributed
um and met the same timelines as if you
had a co-located team and it was about
the clarity of communications you know
when people say you need a co-located
team it's probably because of
inefficient communication right so when
you bump up that communication
um to a level that event modeling does
uh you say well you know I can I can do
a distributed team in different time
zones I'm I'm way more likely to succeed
um using a a methodology where I have
design guiding people I have the same
vision everyone's pulling the same
direction I have these real uh ways of
communicating my concerns immediately
and not have to wait for an artificial
process to to kick off or my feedback
loops to work yeah I appreciate as well
you mentioned it before that this
approach can actually help reduce the
jumping to technology that a lot of
people often tend to do as soon as you
talk about event sourcing for example
somebody wants to talk about well what
what storage mechanism what persistence
mechanisms mechanism we're going to use
and you know I I in in meetings I ban
product people from using words like
Kafka and kubernetes but unfortunately
the software people are trying to teach
them what those things are oh yeah and I
appreciate that with event modeling
you're sort of taking the how out of the
equation let's talk about why what and
who and once we get that established of
course we need to talk about the
implementation details but the ability
to defer that that is I think another
significant advantage that I'm seeing
from this approach exactly it's a it's
it's a good point you you bring up but
it also is a struggle for a lot of
people who are used to certain ways of
working we're used to our own silos
right this is breaking silos for better
communication and a lot of times when I
see event modeling being done just by
developers because they're the ones that
picked up the practice I see these
things sneaking in right we have uh you
know the recent one I saw we have
upserts in here oh this is upserting
this application a business person
doesn't know what you mean by absurd
right it's like a insert slash update
you know lingo from from Tech techies
right and say that doesn't belong on
there that's not describing the system
um so that's one problem with event
modeling is because people are being
pushed into areas that they're not used
to working at and from the opposite side
the level of participation on the
solution from the business is hard to
get people's time business people are
used to sitting in meetings and talking
just to one another most of the day and
so that's the other challenge of event
modeling is really allowing people to
reach out into to truly collaborate with
the with the others in other roles in
their organization
um so you know again on the silver
bullet hey this thing's going to help me
tomorrow if I adopt it no that's this
requires change uh any better way of
working is not going to allow you to
continue to work using your bad habits
right so Improvement requires change and
and people have to realize that event
modeling requires change to take full
advantage of it you can you know take
aspects of it doesn't mean all or
nothing you can start to move to these
things like uh you know I think I
mentioned if you if you are using jira
you can map these these slices to jira
tickets and so forth so you know that's
just one example but there's lots of
lots of aspects of this uh some there I
think in mural you can link figma for
example to be embedded in there it's
kind of a weird little integration you
have to do I always have trouble doing
it but you'll see more and more of these
types of tooling Integrations I think as
we move forward and so embedding the
designers work straight into an event
model is possible it's been done
I think there's even some companies that
have just done event modeling within
figma and just adding the decorations of
this so it's really you know you can do
it in person on a digital uh whiteboard
or whatever it'll work but yeah that's
uh it's nice
you're harking into something else too
which I think is interesting which you
know well actually two two quick
thoughts one is you mentioned you know
when developers are doing this
oftentimes the the technical stuff leaks
in but this is a great opportunity to
help software Engineers to improve their
communication skills with the business
and to help them learn to speak the
language of the business but but on the
other side of things it seems like
there's also an opportunity here for
non-technical people I mean from
everything you're describing it doesn't
seem like there's significant barriers
to say a product manager or even or ux
designer to be able to sort of lead the
charge on event modeling absolutely and
they should be um it should be an equal
um playing a playing Ground for for
people to collaborate it really should
Empower those that that care and then
get that can take charge that have
domain expertise
Etc it is it's it's leveling the playing
field so you have you know contribution
for from everyone in the organization
and each organization is is different
you know you might have a tech heavy
organization where some of these things
may be highly technical you may have a
high marketing company where you know
you need more input from the people that
are driving the sales uh funnels and the
system should respond to that you may
have you know something else where it's
an entirely different aspect I don't
know but
um the event modeling is meant to allow
any role to to take charge at for the
whole project or parts of the workflow
and have that that common Bond and I
think the the common bond is really what
information is in the system can we
agree on State and have that unified
Vision that has that seasonal borders uh
for roles at all and is is highly usable
by each role and that that's the gift
that kind of fell out of that that
effort initially in my company and I'm
happy that that it just uh
just just happened and you know people
in my organization contributed uh really
well to it like for example the idea of
to-do lists uh our our CTO Nicola
basically said these are these are all
kind of like to-do lists we kind of
worked on it together and said any kind
of process because you got into sagas
and all these Enterprise Integration
patterns and things like that how can we
not do all of that and still move
projects forward with without middleware
and all sorts of other things and
without studying the 50 patterns in the
Enterprise Integration book
um oh it's like if you know every one of
these patterns is really attaining a
goal and when I have a goal like going
to the store and going grocery shopping
I bring a shopping list with me and I
check things off as they're done so this
these to-do lists allow things like
fulfillment documents that you might
find in long-running processes and sagas
and processors a fulfillment document
yeah that's another checklist I got to
do a to-do list so you'll notice in
event modeling any Automation and any of
these where you find these larger
patterns they're always replaced by this
to-do list pattern you have a green box
that's that a processor listens to and
then it issues blue boxes or commands to
other parts of the system or the same
system and it might have you know three
of these steps like that that are locked
together to implement what you would
traditionally see in some Observer
pattern or something else you might or
assignment like you mentioned before or
a saga or or any of these things so that
was a big problem I think in in larger
distributed systems is that you got into
the weeds of tech talk really quickly
and it stopped and it stopped the
participation of of the business people
to say well we have a distributed system
now that has to go to The Architects
it's like no that's not fair
um you need to keep that open that that
channel of communication open and so by
introducing this you know to-do list
pattern or component to a pattern
um is uh you know it keeps the keeps the
the event models simple for others to
understand
that's why there's always on the four
patterns right yeah right now to be
clear you could still use a saga as an
implementation detail but what you're
saying is we can keep that
implementation detail out of the event
modeling so the business is not getting
overwhelmed with technical speak and
patterns absolutely if if you already
have middleware that you're making use
of and patterns and you have projects or
maybe a lot of companies have a platform
team right in the platform project where
they have a lot of these things in there
you don't have to throw that in the
garbage that's not that's not what I'm
saying you you have a better way to
represent what's going on without
needing to unders to kind of bubble up
all the information about the platform
to the business and you know and get
them in the room and say this is how the
technical stuff works it's like they
just want to know that the the system
got to a state they're they're happy
with at this point in the workflow and
you know having that separation between
understanding and implementation is
really really key that's great well I'm
sure we could go on and on and on but
this has been a fascinating conversation
and and at this point how can listeners
find out more about event modeling if
they're interested in digging deeper
yeah Event Event modeling is on event
modeling.org it's spelled with one L
it's an American spelling of uh modeling
so those that are spelling in in grammar
uh folks I do apologize but it is valid
I did check um I also wanted it to be
kind of uh different than what you would
have and also on I think on logos and
all that a single L from a design
perspective looks better than two L's so
eventmodeling.org for sure or just
Google event modeling because uh it'll
match the other spelling too so it's a
top hit that will come up I'm available
also on on Twitter and I have a Twitter
account specifically for event modeling
and event Centric tweets which is uh its
own account
uh and uh of course if you're if you're
looking to to get into touch with us you
know to to help Implement your own
Solutions using event modeling and event
sourcing adapted group is a great place
to go that's that's a group of people
that have only been doing this for the
last seven years
um and uh have basically given birth to
this uh approach through through trying
to do the right thing on projects over
many years and um yeah if you want to
get a hold of them as well or work with
them uh adaptagroup.com uh is is one way
but of course I I can point you that if
you get a hold of me on any of these
channels also I'm on LinkedIn and other
other
social media platforms awesome well Adam
thanks so much for joining me on the
show today Jeff thank you it's been the
pleasure always love talking about this
and thank you so much for for having me
absolutely this is Jeff Doolittle for
software engineering radio thanks so
much for listening
thanks for listening to SC radio and
educational program brought to you by
Tripoli software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at sc.radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under created Commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening
[Music]